[Music]
there have been calls to ban the
advertising of sugary cereals to
children for nearly a half century a
product that Harvard nutrition Professor
Jean Mayer referred to as sugarcoated
nothings in a senate hearing on
nutrition education he said properly
speaking they ought to be called seral
flavored candy rather than sugarcoated
cereals the senate committee invited the
major man manufacturers of children's
cereals to testify and they initially
said yes until they heard what kind of
questions they were going to be asked uh
one serial industry representative
candidly admitted why they decided to
boycott the hearing they simply didn't
have persuasive answers for why they're
trying to sell kids breakfast
candy in the Mad Men age before the
consumer movement was In Bloom ad
company Executives were more willing to
talk frankly about the purpose of their
ads and how they felt about aiming the
ads at the quote unquote child Market a
quote from the executive director of
Kellogg's ad firm our primary goal is to
sell products to children not educate
them when you sell a woman a product and
she goes into the store and finds your
brand isn't in stock she'll probably
forget about it but when you sell a kid
on your product if he can't get it he
will throw himself on the floor stamp
his feet and cry you can't get a
reaction like that out of an
adult sugary cereals are the number one
food advertised to kids but not to worry
the industry will just
self-regulate the children's food and
beverage advertising initiative was
launched in which all the big serial
companies pledged they would only Market
healthier dietary choices to kids the
candy industry signed on too how did
that go they pledged not to advertise to
kids yet after the initiative went into
effect kids actually saw more candy ads
take Hershey for example doubled their
advertising to children while at the
same time pledging not to the cereal
companies got to decide for themselves
their own definitions of quote unquote
healthier dietary choices so that should
give us some sense of how serious they
are at protecting children they chose
fro loops and Reese's peanut butter
Puffs consisting of up to 44% Sugar by
weight
those are what they classified as
healthier dietary choices what are their
unhealthy choices turns out what they
did is basically just set the limit
based more on what they were already
selling than what might be best for
children now they've since revised that
down to only allow cereals that are 38%
Sugar by weight but look even if they're
only a third sugar that means kids are
effectively eating a spoonful of sugar
for every three spoons of serial not
exactly a healthier dietary
Choice the Federal Trade Commission
tried stepping in back in 1978 but
industry poured in so many millions of
lobbying might that Congress basically
threatened to yank the entire agency's
funding should they mess with big seral
demonstrating just how powerful Market
forces are compared to those that can be
mobilized on behalf of
children the political post-traumatic
stress induced by the aggressive attacks
on the FTC led to a 25-year Hiatus in
federal efforts to reign in food
marketing aimed at children but finally
enter the inter agency working group
voluntary principles designed to
encourage stronger and more meaningful
self-regulation proposed by the Federal
Trade Commission CDC FDA and USDA with
the radical suggestion of not marketing
children's cereals that are over 26%
pure sugar
not a single one of the top 10 breakfast
cereals marketed to children would meet
that Standard General Mills shot back
that such proposed nutrition standards
were arbitrary capricious and
fundamentally flawed no surprise since
literally every single cereal they
Market wouldn't make the cut to suggest
voluntary standards would
unconstitutionally violate their right
to free speech under the First Amendment
to which the FTC basically said uh let
me get you a dictionary voluntary how
could suggesting voluntary guidelines
violate the constitution that's how
freaked out the industry is though at
even the notion of meaningful guidelines
one grossers association called the
proposed nutrition principles the most
bizarre and unconscionable they had ever
seen so what happened again agency
funding was jeopardized and so the FTC
called the inter agency proposal off
at every level of government the food
and beverage Industries have won fight
after fight nearly never losing a
significant political battle in the
United States we just got beat one of
the child advocacy organizations said
money
wins and it took lots of money 175
million of big food lobbying but
apparently enough to buy the White
House's silence as the inter agency
proposal got killed up off as one Obama
adviser put it you can tell someone to
eat less fat consume more fiber more
fruits and vegetables and less sugar but
if you start naming
Foods you cross the
line I'm upset with the White House the
chair of the Senate health committee
said they went wobbly in the knees and
when it comes to Children's Health they
shouldn't go wobbly in the knees
[Music]